Guide to the Samuel Shaffer papers, 1948-1982 MS2091
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Samuel Shaffer papers
1948-1982
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Shaffer, Samuel
MS2091
19 Linear Feet
Collection consist primarily of Shaffer's Newsweek files (telexes, carbons, xeroxes of what he filed during his tenure with that news magazine) and typescripts of his book "On and Off the Floor." Both the files and the book typescripts are heavily annotated by Shaffer.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
Currently unknown
Biographical Note
Samuel Shaffer (1910-1995) received his bachelor of arts degree in 1931 from The George Washington University, graduating cum laude. He pursued graduate study at the University of Michigan (1931) and at the University of Chicago (1932-1933). He began his journalist career as a reporter From 1936-42, for the "Washington Herald," later the "Washington Times Herald." From 1942-45, he served as a combat correspondent in the U.S. Marines Corps. For his military service in, World War II, Shaffer received the Purple Heart, two battle stars, and the Presidential Unit Citation. After his military service, Shaffer was employed by "Newsweek" magazine as a reporter in New York city (1945-46) and in 1947 was promoted to Chief Congressional Correspondent, a position which he held until 1975.
In 1945 Shaffer's first book, "Betio Beachhead: U.S. Marines' Own Story of the Battle for Tarawa," co-authored with Earl J. Wilson, Jim G. Lucas and C. Peter Zurlinden, was published by G.P. Putnam's Sons. His second book, "On and Off the Floor: Thirty Years as a Correspondent on Capitol Hill," was published by "Newsweek" in 1980. Shaffer is a member of the National Press Club, the White House Correspondents Association, the Periodical Galleries Association, of which he was president (1975-76), and The George Washington University Faculty and Alumni Club.
Samuel Shaffer was born in Washington, D.C. on July 10, 1910 to Morris and Fannie (Siegel) Shaffer. On July 9, 1933 he married a fellow-journalist, Helen Buchalter. They had three children. Helen died on July 18, 1978. Mr. Shaffer died in 1995.
[This exerpt is from Locher, Frances C. Contem orar Authors Volume 104 (Michigan: Gale Research Company, 1982), 424.]
Collection Scope and Content
This collection consist primarily of Shaffer's Newsweek files (telexes, carbons, xeroxes of what he filed during his tenure with that news magazine) and typescripts of his book "On and Off the Floor." Both the files and the book typescripts are often annotated by Shaffer.
Collection Organization
Organized into three series: Chronological files, Correspondence, and Book typescript.
Washington (D.C.); Chief Congressional Correspondent; War correspondents; Journalism; Shaffer, Samuel; George Washington University--Alumni and alumnae; Newsweek, inc; George Washington University
- Chronological files, 1948-1976; MS2091 Series 1; 17 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  series contains Shaffer's copy filed for various sections of "Newsweek" (Nation, Washington Trends, Foreign, Periscope, "Biz", etc.) from 1948-75, final stories on the 1976 presidential campaign, revisions of the stories (addenda/corrections), interviews, and correspondence with his New York editors. Shaffer's submissions are most numerous on Congressional activities, other stories deal with specific pieces of legislation, such as Taft-Hartley, labor, farm, school, trade, and crime bills, government agencies and commissions (CIA, Voice of America, Supreme Court, FBI, SEC, and USIA), military issues; and espionage/un-American activities. Other submissions focus on economic issues, social concerns such as civil rights, welfare, poverty and housing. There are a also a number of files covering disarmament, the U-2 incident, the Cuban crisis, the Nuclear Proliferation and Test Ban treaties, as well as U.S. involvement in the Middle East and Indochina (Laos, Cambodia and Vietnam). Much of the material in this series has never appeared in print.
  - Chronological files, 02/1948-03/1948 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    [from original finding aid] Isacson election; Un-American Activities; American wives with foreign husbands; Maynard's testimony; Notes from Capitol Hill; ERP.- the story in the House; Olea query; Taxes; History of Federal Margarine Legislation; Wallace in Texas; House debate on ERP
  - Chronological files, 04/1948 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    [from original finding aid] Wallace Testimony; Oleo; Spain and ERP; Anti-Communist Legislation; Congressional Probe of Central Intelligence Agency; 70-groups; House Program for 70-Group Air Force M; House Action on Air Force Appropriations; 6leo; Dossiers
  - Chronological files, 05/1948 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    [from original finding aid] Congress and UN; Air Force Appropriations; Mundt Bill; Hoffman "Secrets" Bill; "Voice of America" Script on Utah; Draft; Florida gov query; Voice of America and the Utah Script; Reciprocal Trade Extension; Voice of America Rumpus; Reciprocal trade
  - Chronological files, 06/1948-08/1948 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    [from original finding aid] Voice of America query; ERP Appropriations bill; Governor Blue of Iowa; Memo on 80th Congress Roundup; Hugh Scott; Uranium Rush; Floor microphones at Philadelphia; Wilson Wyatt and the vice presidency; Memo on VP nomination; Republican plans for coming session; Add to memo on Republican plans for special session; Truman message and the Congress; The Congress
  - Chronological files, 09/1948-11/1948 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    [from original finding aid] Note: this memo is an add to Fitz's memo on your; Iowa vote query Atom Espionage J Parwell Thomas query Senate Races House outlook; Radio actives of Republicans House Election Legislative program; The 81st Congress; what role will Dixiecrats and Republicans play
  - Chronological files, 12/1948 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    [from original finding aid] Memo on Congress; Electoral College Reform; Add to Electoral College story; Where is GOP going; Hiss-Chambers; Add to Hiss Chambers; Attention: Toledano; Hiss-Chambers
  - Chronological files, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    [from original finding aid] North Atlantic Pact Acheson; Rayburn's powers The Congress: Public Housing; The Congress Judge Kaufman Spies Farm Legislation
  - Chronological files, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    [from original finding aid] Hoffman and the EGA appropriations; Your housing questions; Congress and the Brannan Plan; Developments on atomic policy?; Judge Kaufman; Arms program; Congressional Reaction to Clark Appointment; Reciprocal Trade; The Congress; Wherry Atomic Bill
  - Chronological files, 01/1949 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    [from original finding aid] Folo on spy story; Eighty-first Congress; State of Union Address; The counting of electoral votes; The House
  - Chronological files, 02/1949 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    [from original finding aid] Labor Bill on House side; Query on commy espionage legislation; Joint Economic Committee Hearings; Connally and the North Atlantic Pact; Vets pensions; The Congress; The Congress
  - Chronological files, 03/1949 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    [from original finding aid] Congress; The House Senate filibuster Wallgren Rent Control; Rankin Pension bill; Senator Wagner query
  - Chronological files, 04/1949 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    [from original finding aid] Oleo; Recession roundup story Rent Control Labor Legislation Labor Bill; Veteran's legislation Taft Hartley repeal in House (Rep Norris Cotton - N Hampshire) (Letters from Shaffer) Taft-Hartley repeal debate
  - Chronological files, 05/1949 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    [from original finding aid] Taft-Hartley repeal; Taft-Hartley developments; The Mills Tax Plan; Cigarette tax debate; Senator Douglas and the Pork Bill; Louis Johnson and Consolidated; The Congress
  - Chronological files, 06/1949-07/1949 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    [from original finding aid] The Congress The Congress The Congress; The Congress
  - Chronological files, 08/1949-09/1949 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    [from original finding aid] Brannan Plan Minimum Wage Arms Program; Displaced Persons Legislation Minimum Wage; Arms Bill; The Congress; The Congress--aid to China
  - Chronological files, 10/1949-12/1949 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    [from original finding aid] The 81st Congress, first session: review and analysis; The Congress; Junkets; Jordan, Groves and the A-Bomb Yarn; The Congress
  - Chronological files, 01/1950 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    [from original finding aid] Congress Week; State of the Union;- Message with Congressional Reaction; Oleo; The Rules Committee; Korea Bill; The Rules Fight; FEPC; Congress on Taxes; Hydrogen Bomb Roundup-The Congressional End
  - Chronological files, 02/1950 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    [from original finding aid] Sidebar material Ofi H-bomb; Electoral College Refbrm; Korean Aid; FEPC; Excise Taxes; The Senate and the Central Arizona Project; FEPC; McCarthy
  - Chronological files, 03/1950 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    [from original finding aid] Congress and State Department "Reds"; Congress Week-Part Two; Congress Week; Congress-The Housing Defeat; (Letter from McCarthy to Tydings); The Kerr Bill; McCarthy
  - Chronological files, 04/01/1950-04/08/1950 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    [from original finding aid] McCarthy Foreign Aid; Lattimore and McCarthy Congress week
  - Chronological files, 04/15/1950-04/29/1950 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    [from original finding aid] Brannan and the Captive Audience Congress Week Congress Week Congress Week
  - Chronological files, 05/1950 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    [from original finding aid] Congress Week-Part Two, Congress Week Congress Week Congress Week
  - Chronological files, 06/1950 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    [from original finding aid] Acheson Addresses Joint Session; Amerasia; Congress Week; (Republican Conference); Congress Week, CONTD; Congress Week; (Note from Lindley)
  - Chronological files, 07/1950 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    [from original finding aid] Congress Week; Congress Week, continued; Congress Week; Congress Week; Dulles Luncheons; political Blackmail and Passamaguoddy; Congress Week; Congress Week, Second Section; Congress
  - Chronological files, 08/1950 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    [from original finding aid] Congress Week; (Fracas in Buchanan Lobbying Cmte); Congress Week
  - Chronological files, 09/1950 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    [from original finding aid] Congress Week; Second Session Roundup; The Grilling of General Marshall; Congress Week; Memphis Press - Scimitar Editorial
  - Chronological files, 11/1950 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    [from original finding aid] Campbellite Sect Congress and the Elections The Senate Leadership Hawaiian Statehood Congress Week
  - Chronological files, 12/1950 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    [from original finding aid] Congress Week; Congress Week - Part Two; Congress Week; (the case of Anna M.Rosenberg) Congress Week
  - Chronological files, 02/1952 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    [from original finding aid] Senate Election Qutlook; Congress Week; Washington Trends Checker from shaffer; The South in Revolt; Congress Week, continued - page seven; Sen. Kern; Latam from Shaffer; Radio from Shaffer 2-28-52; (Rayburn query) Politics
  - Chronological files, 03/1952 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    [from original finding aid] Nation(Lavine) from Shaffer Congress Week; Congress Week continued - page eight Congress Week, continued - page thirteen The Television Squabble Moody Bill On Senate Bill 2352 Congress Week; Congress Week, continued (page seven) Congress Week, continued (page eleven) Politics Politics; Politics (continued) page four Congress Week; Congress Week, continued (page five) Congress Week, continued (page nine) Nation from Shaffer The New Jersey queries; Democratic response to Eisenhower gains; Lavine from Shaffer
  - Chronological files, 03/1952 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    [from original finding aid] Congress, continued (page eleven); The effect of the New Hampshire primaries; Congress Week; MacMuir from Shaffer; Nation from Shaffer; Nation Checker from shaffer
  - Chronological files, 04/02/1952-04/06/1952 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    [from original finding aid] The City Bloc query Publicity from Shaffer The political picture Nation, etc., from Shaffer Re your #3
  - Chronological files, 04/10/1952-04/30/1952 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    [from original finding aid] The political roundup The political picture FBI and corruption cleanup; Politics; Trends from Shaffer; Congress Week; Primaries; Congress Week; Congress Week, continued (page nine); Congress Week, continued (page thirteen); Congress Week, continued (page eighteen)
  - Chronological files, 05/03/1052-05/31/1952 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    [from original finding aid] Steel seizure poll Re your #3 Press from Shaffer Congress; The Correspondents poll Congress Week, continued (page twelve) Congress Week, continued (page six) Congress Week; Washington Trends from Shaffer Bills Affecting Business
  - Chronological files, 05/23/1952-05/31/1952 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    [from original finding aid] Page sixteen; Congress Week, continued (page two) Congress Week Congress Week Congress Politics; Congress and steel; Congress Week, continued (page seven) Congress Week, continued (page 10+) Congress Week, continued (page twenty) Congress Week Congress Week, continued - page eight
  - Chronological files, 06/05/1952-06/11/1952 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    [from original finding aid] Re your query #1 of 6/5/52; Congress and the steel decision; Ike's speech; Comfort stations and economic controls; Re your query #5 of 6/5/52 Controls bill Politics, Republican Politics, Republican
  - Chronological files, 06/13/1952-06/28/1952 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    [from original finding aid] Congress Week; Congress Week, continued (page four); Congress Week, continued (page ten); Congress Week, continued (page twelve); Congress Week, continued (page fifteen); Congress Week; Economic controls; Re your #7 of 6/28/52; Roundup of the 82nd Congress - second session; Convention;; 'v'
  - Chronological files, 07/1952-08/1952 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    [from original finding aid] MacMuir from Shaffer (Re query #8 Wash. Trends);Washington Trends from Shaffer;The Democratic Candidate Picture;Page four;Newsweek;Newsweek ;Newsweek;Southern Primaries;Washington Trends from Shaffer;Jim Howard from Shaffer;Washington Trends from Shaffer;People Today from Ernest K.Lindley and Samuel Shaffer;Washington Trends from Shaffer;Political Picture
  - Chronological files, 09/1952-10/1952 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    [from original finding aid] Crawford from Shaffer (Taft-Ike merger) Lemon car law; N-ll Chairmen and your query #5 of today Congressional leaders
  - Chronological files, 11/1952-12/1952 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    [from original finding aid] Brown from Shaffer Washington Trends from Shaffer Martin Interview Michigan Election Contest Kenneth Orawford Bridges Interview Letters from Shaffer Congressional Trends
  - Chronological files, 01/16/1953 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    [from original finding aid] Congress Week; Johnson Interview; Congress Week; Mac Muir from Shaffer; Section ewe of Title 18; Your query #2; Wayne Morse Interview
  - Chronological files, 02/1953 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    [from original finding aid] Congress Week, continued - page nine; Congress Week, continued - page twelve; Congress Week; RE your #2; Washington Trends from §haffer
  - Chronological files, 03/1953-04/1953 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    [from original finding aid] The Congress and Ike Washington Trends Tidelands Legislation Correction 2-Gongress (Interview) Dulles; McCarthy, Dulles and Stassen Joe McCarthy Taft Interview; Questions for Interview w. Mr.Sam Rayburn, Minotity Leader of the House; Washington Trends from Shaffer
  - Chronological files, 05/1953-06/26/1953 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    [from original finding aid] Taft and Knowland; Wash. Trend query #3 6/14; Congress Week; Congress Week, continued (page 11); Washington trends from Shaffer
  - Chronological files, 07/18/1953-08/1953 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    [from original finding aid] Congress Week Congress Week, continued Congress Week Re guery #5; Washington trends from Shaffer-Herewith Taber Interview Re Taber Interview N10 Congress Round-up Chicago Democratic Meeting
  - Chronological files, 09/1953-10/1953 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    [from original finding aid] Biz from Shaffer (attention cleaton); Congress and the Administration; Politics; 2-election; the Virginia election; Politics; Query on Ike's campaigning; Brownell; Politics
  - Chronological files, 11/28/1953 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    [from original finding aid] Politics and Congress; The Harry Dexter White Case; Washington Trends from Shaffer; The White Affair Washington Trends from Shaffer; Washington Trends from Shaffer; Nation from Shaffer - (interview w. Senator Joseph R. McCarthy)
  - Chronological files, 12/1953 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    [from original finding aid] Congress and the Legislative program Washington Trends from Shaffer and Hadley Democratic figures; Periscope (Debs Myers) from Shaffer and Lindley Myers from Shaffer (Re your #8 - Washington Trends query)
  - Chronological files, 12/1953 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    [from original finding aid] Von Wettburg from Shaffer; Nixon Cover Story Memo; The Humphrey story; (Interview); Congress Week; Congress Week - page ten; Congress Week (page 18); Congress Week; 11-Congress
  - Chronological files, 12/1953 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    [from original finding aid] Congress Week, continued - page six Congress Week, continued - page 12 Congress Week, continued - page 17 Insert A; The Bohlen Affair Congress Congress Week; Congress Week, continued - page seven The files
  - Chronological files, 12/1953 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    [from original finding aid] Congress Week Congress Week; Congress Week, continued - page nine Congress Week; Congress Week, continued-page five Congress Week; Congress Week, continued-page nine Congress Week, continued-page thirteen Reorganisation
  - Chronological files, 12/1953 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    [from original finding aid] New lead material for trends; Ike and Congress; Congress Week; Congress Week; Congress Week - section two - page nine; Congress Week - section two - page 15
  - Chronological files, 01/01/1954-01/15/1954 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    [from original finding aid] Dulles' Gloomy Report; Politics in 1954; Controlling McCarthy; Congress; State of the Union Message; Congress Week; Congress Week, continued-page seven
  - Chronological files, 01/16/1954-01/31/1954 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    [from original finding aid] Congress, continued-page four Congress week, continued-page eleven Radio from Shaffer Congress Week Periscope (Myers) and copy desk from Shaffer; (Re your #3 and Washington Trends second take.) Len Hall 12-Hall
  - Chronological files, 02/01/1954-02/15/1954 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    [from original finding aid] Congress Week Legislative program McAllister from Shaffer Senator Humphrey Defends Himself Politics Periscope from Shaffer
  - Chronological files, 02/16/1954-02/28/1954 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    [from original finding aid] Periscope from Shaffer; 3-Periscope; Periscope from Shaffer; Congress Week (Indo-China Affair); Congress Week, continued--page eleven (Beeson; nomination); Re Saltonstall - Gore debate Is Congress going to reform itself? Congress Week Congress Week, continued; page sixteen (Dulles and; Congress)
  - Chronological files, 03/1954 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    [from original finding aid] Congress Week (McCarthy vs. Ike); 12-Congress; N-16 Reform; Nation fjcqm Shaffer
  - Chronological files, 04/1954-09/1954 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    [from original finding aid] Washington Trends from Shaffer (Maine elections); Mitchell-McKinney; Norris Cotton; Communist Party; Washington Trends from Shaffer; Sidelights on Censure; Joe McCarthy
  - Chronological files, 10/13/1954 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    [from original finding aid] Nation (Toledano) from Shaffer; Washington Trends from Shaffer; Nation (Myers) from Shaffer; Re your #10; Debs Myers f. Shaffer; Debs Myers f. Shaffer; Davis from Shaffer; Nation (Myers) from Shaffer; Televising Congress
  - Chronological files, 11/1954 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    [from original finding aid] Senate Shifts in Special Session Election Analysis; Nixon; Nixon Interview; Periscope (Hadley) from Shaffer Knowland Interview-Foreign Policy (Lyndon Johnson Interview) Memo on Censure Impact
  - Chronological files, 12/1954 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    [from original finding aid] Knowland; White House Meeting Science from Shaffer Ike draft memo; Housing Investigation report Nation (Myers) from Shaffer Nation (Myers) from Shaffer (Interview with Sen.; John B. McClellan) Legislative Outlook
  - Chronological files, 03/18/1955-03/24/1955 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    [from original finding aid] Memo on Formosa Mail; Bipartisanship; Myers from Roberts, Shaffer, Crawford (Republicans); Nation (Myers) from Shaffer; Nation from Shaffer; Nation from Shaffer; Congress and the Yalta Papers
  - Chronological files, 03/1955 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    [from original finding aid] Re your #10 - Yalta (03/19/1955); (Taxes and Congressional Roundup Memo); Campbell Confirmation Memo; Knowland Interview; Nation (Myers) from Shaffer; Tax Memo; Tax; Democratic Candidates for lead; George; Goldwater; George Interview; Congress and the Big Four Meeting; Nation (Myers) from Shaffer 05/13/1955
  - Chronological files, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Chronological files, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Chronological files, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Chronological files, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Chronological files, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    [from original finding aid] Politics; Query (McAllister) from Shaffer; Congress; Margello from Shaffer; The Stevenson visit; Power Play memo; Herewith are the Lyndon Johnson remarks; Myers from Shaffer--09/29/1955 (Interview w. Sen.; Styles Bridges Re your #3 Debs Myers from Shaffer
  - Chronological files, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    [from original finding aid] Debs Myers from Shaffer (Washington Trends); Nation (Ivins) from Shaffer (Dirksen); Foreign (de Borchgrave) from Shaffer (Nixon); Washington Trends from Shaffer; Nation (Myers) from Shaffer; Nation (Myers) from Shaffer; Additional Washington Trends; Washington trends, continued; (Stevenson); How about substituting these for paras 11; through 15; Here are some quotes for you: Washington Trends from Shaffer, Weintal Interview with Rep. Leslie C. Arends Debs Myers from Shaffer Myers from Shaffer-11/4/55 Debs from Shaffer; Meys from Shaffer (Hubert Humphrey) Quotes pro and con on Adlai Stevenson Election and politics roundup
  - Chronological files, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    [from original finding aid] The Cross Case; Conway from Shaffer (Re your no.4 of 11/20/1955); (Mrs Johnson--low calorie diets...) Memo on foreign policy issue Biz from Shaffer (Note from Rowen to Elliott...; (tax)); Correction (Re: N-18-Democrats) Nation (Ivins) from Shaffer (Nixon) Education from Washington (Nixon) Myers from Shaffer-12/06/1955 (goldwater) Knowland; Goldwater Interview Knowland Interview Re N-16 Violin - Significance
  - Chronological files, 1956 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    [from original finding aid] State-of-union speech analysis; Notes on Dulles press conference; Congress Week; The Dulles Article; The Gas Bill fight; Neuberger; Congress Week; Congress Week roundup-7; Congress Week, continued (page seven)
  - Chronological files, 1956 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    [from original finding aid] Congress Week, continued (page eight) Sugar Bill; Congress Week roundup; Box with gas story; Natural gas; The Natural gas imbroglio; Nation (Myers) from Shaffer; Add to Democratic dilemma; Add to Gas Bill story; Congress Week 01/28/1956
  - Chronological files, 1956 (Box 7, Folder 3)